自由と権利が欲しくないか
Don't you desire freedom and rights, Hohenheim?
ホーエンハイム
Do you plan to let your life end as a slave,
人間としての権利を手に入れないまま
奴隷で一生を終わる気か
without even obtaining your basic rights as a human?
If so, you might as well be living in this stuffy flask.
それでは息苦しいフラスコの中に
いるのと同じだ
Why?!
なぜだ
All right!
よっしゃ　畳み込め エド
Finish him, Ed!
Why am I, someone who has obtained God,
なぜ神を手に入れた私がたかが人間の…
being defeated by the bare hands...
...of a mere human alchemist?
錬金術師に素手で…
He did it!
やった　やった～
All right!
やった～勝った～
You showed him!
Man the fuck up!
しっかりしねぇか
何飛ばされてんだ
Why are you getting swept away?!
すっ　すまん
M-My bad!
Stone...
石…
Philosopher's stone!!
賢者の石
賢者の石　よこせ
Give me your philosopher's stone!
Shit!
ヤベぇ
グリード
Greed!!
バカ野郎
Idiot, you're going to get yourself dragged in!
巻き込まれるぞ　放せ
Let go!
断る
I refuse!
オレが皇帝になるために
In order for me to become the Emperor, I need you!
お前にはいてもらわなきゃならないんだ
That's just impossible!
無理だ　オレ様はもともと
I was born from Father to begin with.
おやじ殿から生まれてんだ
リン·ヤオの体より
The force that's pulling me toward him is stronger than the one pulling me toward Lin Yao!
あっちに引かれる力が強くて
どうにもなんねぇ
Nothing can be done!
あきらめるな　グリード  ふんばれ
Don't give up, Greed!
Keep trying!
Shit!
ヤバい
My body...!
体が…
God dammit!!
こなくそ
Well, it's a few ranks lower than being the king of the world,
世界の王からかなりランクは下がるが
シンの皇帝も悪くねぇか
but I guess I wouldn't mind becoming the Emperor of Xing.
We're gonna fight together, partner.
一緒に戦おうぜ　相棒
That's the spirit!
そうこなくっちゃ
What are you...
何を…
And this is goodbye.
ここでさよならだ
お前まで
There's no need for you to be absorbed by him along with me.
おやじ殿に吸収されるこたぁねぇ
H-Hang on, Greed!
ちょっ　ちょっと待て　グリード
You just said that we were going to fight together!
一緒に戦うって言ったじゃないか
こんな　だまし討ちみたいなことをして　お前
This is foul play, dammit!
I thought you never told lies!
お前はウソをつかないのを
信条にしてたんじゃないのか
You can't let it end like this!
こんな終わり方…
You totally fell for it though, shitty brat!
まんまとだまされやがって
しょんべんガキが
That was my first and final lie.
オレ様の最初で最後のウソよ
Lan Fan has a philosopher's stone with her.
ランファンが賢者の石を持ってる
Take it home with you, kid.
それ持って帰りな　ガキ
Wait...
待て…
Wait!
待て
Wait, Greed!!
待て　グリード
Come, Lan Fan!
来い　ランファン
Peace.
あばよ
Greed!
グリード
Greed!!
Curse you, Greed!!
おのれぇ　グリード
I was able to free myself from an annoying brat.
うるさいガキからうまく分離できたぜ
Why do you revolt against your father, Greed?!
グリード　なぜ父に逆らう
遅めの反抗期だよ　おやじ殿
Just going through a late puberty, pops.
With this carbonization ability you gave me,
あんたのくれたこの炭化能力で
I'll turn us into the most brittle form of carbon, charcoal!
いちばんもろい
ボロ炭に変身してやらぁ
こざかしい
You little...!
Begone, fool!
消えよ　愚か者
Greed!!
グリード
Damn, I guess this is it...
くそっ　ここまでかよ…
Take a look in the damn mirror, brat.
なんて目で見やがる
しょんべんガキが
仲間ってのは魂でつながってるんだよ
Friends are connected by the soul!
There's no way you'd forget!
忘れるわけないだろうが
Want to join us?
仲間にならねぇか
行くとこないなら　一緒に来いよ
If you've got nowhere else to go, come with us.
Man, both Lin and the midget totally made a fool out of me.
ったく　リンもチビも　随分
なめた態度とってくれたもんだ
That was plenty...
十分だ…
Yeah, that was enough for me...
もう十分だ
I don't need anything else...
もう　なんにもいらねぇや
Peace out, soul... brothers...
じゃあな　魂の…友よ…
You guys...
みんな…
My stones...
石が…賢者の石が…
My philosopher's stones...
W-What?
なっ　なんだ　なんだ
What is this?!
Go back to where you were born,
生まれた場所に帰れ
Dwarf in the Flask, Homunculus!
フラスコの中の小人  ホムンクルス
Why?!
なぜだ
私は知りたかった
I wanted to learn everything about this world!
この世のすべてを
何ものにも縛られず
I wanted to live freely in this vast world without being bound by anyone!
自由に広い世界に
私は
I...!
Why?!
なぜだ
なぜ私のものにならぬ
Why won't you become mine?!
神よ　何が気に入らないのだ
God, what are you unhappy with?!
Because you don't believe in yourself.
お前が己を信じないからだ
You were born from humans after stealing other's power,
他人の力を盗み
人から生まれたもののくせに
and yet, you were just clinging on to God the entire time.
神とやらにしがみついていただけだ
You haven't grown up at all.
お前自身が成長しておらん
七つの欲を切り離せば
Did you think you'd be able to surpass humans if you let go of your seven desires?
人を超えられるとでも思ったか
Don't make me laugh!
笑わせるな
私は完全な存在になりたかった
I wanted to become a perfect being!
I wanted to learn everything about this world!
この世のすべてを知りたかった
What's wrong with wanting that?!
欲して何が悪い
What's wrong with desiring it?!
望んで何が悪い
What's wrong with wishing for it?!
願い求めて何が悪い
Who...
なんだ…なんだ　お前は
Who the hell are you?!
Who?!
なんだっていうんだ
Who the hell do you think you are?!
何様のつもりだ　お前は
I'm the existence which you all refer to as "The World."
私は
お前たちが世界と呼ぶ存在
And "Universe," and "God,"
あるいは宇宙　あるいは神
and "Truth," and "All," and "One."
あるいは真理
あるいは全　あるいは一
And I am also yourself.
そして　私はお前だ
Truth is what gives one the most fitting form of despair to insure them not to become conceited.
思い上がらぬよう
正しい絶望を与えるのが真理
He gives humans the most fitting form of despair to make sure humans don't become conceited.
人間が思い上がらぬよう
正しい絶望を与える
That is Truth.
それが真理だ
だから　お前にも絶望を与えよう
Thus, I'll also give you despair.
I don't want to go back!
戻りたくない…嫌だ…
No!
Stop! I don't want to be bound there forever!
やめろ
そこに縛られ続けるのは嫌だ
No! No!
嫌だ　嫌だ　嫌だ～
No!!
思い上がった者に絶望を
Despair to the ones who become swelled with pride.
私はどうすればよかったのだ
What else should I have done?!
お前が望んだ結末だ
This is the end you desired.
What should I have done?!
どうすればよかったのだ
You probably foresaw the answer.
お前はその答えを見ていただろうに
なんだ
What? What happened?
どうなった　勝ったのか
Did we win?
Yes.
はい　ですが
But... Alphonse has yet to come back from the other side.
アルフォンス君が
あちらから戻っていません
I'm... I'm so sorry...!
ごめんなさい…
It's not your fault.
お前のせいじゃない
アルの判断だ
It was Al's decision.
Ed, we have a toll.
エド　通行料ならある
Use it, it's a philosopher's stone.
使え　賢者の石だ
これでアルを取り戻せ
Use this to get Al back.
I can't.
ダメだ
オレたちが元の体に戻るのに
We promised we'd never use a philosopher's stone to get our bodies back.
賢者の石は使わないと
アルと約束した
There has to be another way.
方法はあるはずだ　必ず
There HAS to be.
Think...!
考えろ　考えるんだ
Think!
Don't stop thinking!
思考を止めるな
Edward.
エドワード
オレの命を使って
Use my life to bring Alphonse back.
アルフォンスを取り戻せ
I've got just enough life left for one.
ちょうど１人分残ってる
Idiot!
バカ野郎
そんなことできるわけないだろ
There's no way I could do something like that!
It's our own fault that we lost our bodies!
オレたち兄弟が体をなくしたのは
オレたちのせいだ
I've said so many times that we won't use other's lives to get Al back!
アルを取り戻すのに
人の命は使わねぇって
さんざん言ってるだろうが
Besides, why the hell do YOU have to give your life up?!
だいたい　なんで
てめぇが命懸ける必要がある
父親だからだよ
Because I'm your father.
It's not about needs or reasoning.
必要とか　理屈とかじゃない
You two are precious to me.
お前たちが大事なんだ
幸せになってほしいんだ
I want the both of you to live happily.
I'm partially to blame for what happened to your bodies, since I left you to care for yourselves.
お前たちの体が
そうなってしまったのは
ほったらかしにしてきた
オレにも責任がある
I'm sorry.
すまなかった
I've lived enough.
もう十分生きた
Let me do something father-like for just this last time.
最期くらい
父親らしいことをさせてくれ
Don't be ridiculous, you good-for-nothing dad!
バカ言ってんじゃねぇよ  クソおやじ
Don't ever say something like that again!
二度とそんなこと言うな
張っ倒すぞ
I'll punch you!
I'm sorry, Edward...
すまない　エドワード…
Think...!
考えろ　考えろ
Think!
Aren't I supposed to be the youngest state alchemist of all time?!
史上最年少の国家錬金術師だろ
I can use alchemy without a transmutation circle because I saw Truth, right?!
真理を見たお陰で錬成陣なしに
錬金術が使えるんだろ
There has to be a way!
方法はあるはずだ　必ず
There has to be!
I'm sure a lot of people are waiting for the day when you two get your bodies back.
たくさんの人が
あなたたちが元の体に戻る日を
待ってくれてるはずよ
If there's a possibility, you should move forward.
そこに可能性があるならば
前に進むべきだろう
That's right. Don't give up.
そうだ　あきらめるな
There... There has to be something.
何かあるはずだ　何か
Something!
何か…
Sir Al...
アル様…
Sir Al...!
アル様…アル様…
Sir Al!
May is crying so much for Al...
メイ　アルのために
そんなに泣いてくれるのか
Zampano, Donkey Kong, and everyone from Briggs...
ザンパノ　ゴリさん
ブリッグズのみんな…
Major, Lin, Lan Fan...
少佐　リン　ランファン
Master, Dad...
師匠　おやじ…
メイ　ちょっと離れてろ
May, step away for a sec.
That's...!
それは
A human transmutation circle!
人体錬成の陣
I'll be right back.
ちょっと行ってくるわ
鋼の錬金術師　最後の錬成にな
The last transmutation that the Fullmetal Alchemist will ever do.
Ed!
エド
Edward Elric!
エドワード·エルリック
弟を連れ戻しに来たか
So you came to get your brother back.
だが　どうやって
But how are you going to drag an entire human out?
人間１人を引っ張り出す
代価は
What will you sacrifice?
お前の肉体を差し出すか
Your entire body?
代価ならここにあるだろ　でけぇのがよ
There's something huge right here that I can sacrifice.
こいつはオレの真理の扉だ
This is MY Gate of Truth.
ってこたぁどう使おうがオレの自由だ
Which means I can do whatever I want with it.
違うか
Am I wrong?
そうきたか
So that was your plan.
しかし　いいのか
But are you sure about that?
真理の扉を失えば
If you lose your Gate of Truth,
you'll never be able to use alchemy again.
二度と錬金術を使えなくなるぞ
そうだな
Yeah...
確かにこの扉の向こうには
You're right, all of alchemy is on the other side of this gate.
錬金術のすべてがある
でも　お陰で踊らされたよ
But thanks to it, I was manipulated.
真理とかいうものを見せられて
I was shown the Truth, and believed that I could solve everything with alchemy.
錬金術ですべてを解決できると思い込んだ
だけど　それは間違いだった
But I was wrong.
ただの傲慢だ
I was just being arrogant.
錬金術の使えない
You're going to become an ordinary human who can't use alchemy?
ただの人間に成り下がるのか
成り下がるも何も
I'm not going to "become" anything. I've always been an ordinary human.
最初っから　ただの人間だ
合成獣にされた女の子１人助けられない
I'm a puny human who couldn't even save a girl who was turned into a chimera.
ちっぽけな人間だ
いいんだな　本当に
So you're sure you don't mind getting rid of that?
それがなくても
エド
Ed!
鋼の
Fullmetal!
エドワード君
Edward!
エド
Ed!
エドワード·エルリック
Edward Elric!
エド
Ed!
エドワードさん
Mr. Edward!
エド
Ed!
錬金術がなくても
Even if I lose alchemy, I'll still have my friends.
みんながいるって
正解だ　錬金術師
Correct, alchemist!
You've defeated me.
お前はオレに勝った
持っていけ　すべてを
Take everything you want!
勝手口はあっちだ
The back door is over that way,
エドワード·エルリック
Edward Elric.
ムチャしやがって
You were so reckless.
兄さんこそ
Ditto.
さあ　帰ろう　一緒に
Okay, let's go back. Together.
Yeah.
Hey, he's awake!
気づいた
大丈夫か　アルフォンス
You okay, Alphonse?
ザンパノさん
Mr. Zampano and Mr. Darius...
ダリウスさん　みんな…
Everyone...
父さん
Dad!
Yo, welcome back.
おかえり
Yup.
ただいま
Glad to be back.
あったかい
So warm...
アル様…
Sir Al...
アルフォンス様
Sir Alphonse!
メイ
May!
I... I...!
メイは…メイは…
そっか　ごめん
That's right, I'm sorry.
つらいことさせちゃったね
I made you do something you didn't want to do.
ありがとう　メイ
Thanks, May.
ラジオ·キャピタルをお聴きの皆様
To those who are listening to Radio Capital:
本日　アームストロング少将と
Today, the squadrons led by Major General Armstrong and Colonel Mustang
マスタング大佐率いる部隊が
中央司令部議会等を占拠しました
captured Central Headquarters, assembly, and so on.
これは軍上層部の動きを
This was all in order to halt the actions of the upper echelon of the army;
阻止するためのもので
彼らは国民の大多数を犠牲にする
they were planning a massive alchemy experiment that would sacrifice a great number of our citizens.
錬金術の大実験を企てていました
大総統閣下の留守を狙い
Out of the masterminds who were planning on carrying out this evil experiment,
悪逆非道の実験を行おうとした首謀者のうち
クレミン准将とエジソン准将は拘束され
Brigadier General Clemin and Brigadier General Edison were captured,
両将率いる国軍も武装解除されました
and the soldiers who used to be under their command were disarmed.
キング·ブラッドレイ大総統閣下と
Führer President King Bradley and his son, Selim,
ご子息セリムさんは混乱のなかに
lost their lives in the midst of the confusion.
その尊い命を落とされました
マスタング大佐は
Colonel Mustang has voiced his intention to carry on the will of the Führer President and to keep our nation safe,
大総統閣下の遺志を継ぎ
国の安全を堅持
今後の対策を関係各位と
and that he'll consult with all whom it may concern about future measures.
協議すると発言しました
君だろ　私に血をくれたのは
You're the one who gave me blood, right?
自由と権利が欲しくないか
Don't you desire freedom and rights, Hohenheim?
ホーエンハイム
じゃあ　お前の幸せってなんだ
Then what does happiness mean to you?
そうだなぁ
Let's see... I won't ask for anything too extravagant,
ぜいたくは言わないが
このフラスコから
but I guess I'd be happy if I could somehow leave this flask.
出られる身になれば　幸せかな
そうだよなぁ
You're right, Dwarf in the Flask, Homunculus.
フラスコの中の小人　ホムンクルス
お前はオレの血から生まれたんだ
You were born from my blood.
オレは…
I...
ホーエンハイム殿
Sir Hohenheim.
ご子息２人とも
Both of your children have been safely hospitalized.
病院に無事収容しましたぞ
ありがとう  感謝します
Thank you. I appreciate it.
いえ　感謝するのはこちらの方です
No, I should be the one thanking you.
エドワード·エルリックと
Edward Elric and Alphonse Elric.
アルフォンス·エルリック
あの２人の少年がいなければ
If it weren't for those two boys, this country would have fallen.
この国は滅んでいました
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
ありがとう
Thanks.
ただいま　トリシャ
I'm home, Trisha.
エドワードがおやじって呼んでくれたんだ
Edward called me "Dad."
「クソ」が付いてたんだけどなぁ
Though there was a "good-for-nothing" in front of it.
人より長く生き続けるなんて
I always thought that it would be backbreaking to continue living longer than everyone else.
しんどいことばかりだと思ってた
だけど　君や息子たちに会えて
But by meeting you and our sons,
生きててよかったと
I was able to truly appreciate the fact that I was alive, from the bottom of my heart.
心から思えるようになった
充実した人生だった
It was a fulfilling life.
そうさ　十分だ
Yeah... it was more than enough.
ありがとう　トリシャ
Thank you, Trisha.
でも…
But...
やっぱり　死にたくねぇって
...somehow, I still want to live.
思っちゃうなぁ
ほんとオレってしょうがねぇなぁ
I really am a good-for-nothing.
ホーエンハイム
Hohenheim!
なんだい　帰ってたのかい
What, you came home?
バカたれが…
Idiot...
なんて幸せそうな顔して死んでんだい
I've never seen a dead person look so happy.
やっと見つけた　新しい朝は
The new morning we've finally found
Yatto mitsuketa atarashii asa wa
月日が邪魔をする
is being hampered by the past.
Tsukihi ga jama wo suru
向かう先は　「次」じゃなくて
What we chased after wasn't the future,
Mukau saki wa tsugi ja nakute
「過」ばかり追いかけた
but the past so full of remorse.
Sugi bakari oikaketa
鳴り止まない
The ruthless memories won't stop playing;
Nariyamanai yousha nai omoide tachi wa
容赦ない思い出たちは
許してくれそうにもない
they won't be forgiving us for a long time.
Yurushite kuresou nimonai
そろそろかな
It's about now that a teardrop
Sorosoro kana tesaguri tsukareta hoho wo
手探り　疲れた頬を
葛藤がこぼれ落ちる
beings to roll down my fatigued cheeks.
Kattou ga koboreochiru
雨は　いつか止むのでしょうか
Will this rain ever stop?
Ame wa itsuka yamunodeshouka
ずいぶん長い間　冷たい
I've been freezing for a long time.
Zuibun nagai aida tsumetai
雨は　どうして僕を選ぶの
Why does the rain continue to fix on me?
Ame wa doushite boku wo erabuno
包まれて　いいかな
I wonder if it could embrace me.
Tsutsumarete iikana
雨は　止むことを知らずに
Today, the rain falls again;
Ame wa yamu koto wo shirazuni
今日も降り続くけれど
endlessly it falls knowing no end.
Kyou mo furitsuzukukeredo
そっと　差し出した傘の中で
We nestle close to each other to share the warmth
Sotto sashidashita kasa no naka de
温もりに　寄り添いながら
under this umbrella, you gently held out to me.
Nukumori ni yorisoinagara
次回　鋼の錬金術師
日本語字幕仕上げ：XIAOBIN
Fullmetal　Alchemist
The beginning is what comes after the ending.
最終回　『旅路の涯』
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs
Carve out with your own hands a future, filled with hope.
踏み出せ
人生という名の世界に
Next time, Fullmetal Alchemist:
Finale, Journey's End.
Take a step forward into the world called "life."